Finding Aid for Housing Division (University of Michigan) Records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Housing Division (University of Michigan) records 1923-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. Housing Division.
90136 Bimu B6 2
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, and other materials relating to administration of the office; include files relating to operation and naming of University dormitories, especially detailing the establishment of housing policy and the resolution of housing controversies; information on small group housing and off-campus housing with individual files on fraternities and sororities; also files concerning the occupational status and treatment of Japanese-Americans working for the University during World War II, and concerning the housing and training of military personnel on campus during the war.
43 linear feet in 44 boxes
1 oversize volumes
2 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred to the library beginning in 1952 by the Office of Student Affairs (Donor no. 2948 ) and by its successor the Office of Student Services (Donor no. 5013 ). Periodic accessions continue from Housing Division (Donor no. 8160).
The records of the Housing Division are open with the exception of several student papers which are restricted under terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act.
The Housing Division record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 40
The University of Michigan's role in providing housing for students has varied dramatically through time. In the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, the university took very minimal responsibility for student housing. Around the turn of the century, however, the dean of women began to show interest in the subject. After years of effort, the university's first official residence for women, Helen Newberry Residence, was opened in 1915, followed by Martha Cook (1915), Alumnae House (1917), Betsey Barbour House (1920) and Adelia Cheever House (1921). A crowded housing market led to the construction of additional women's dormitories in the 1930s, including Mosher-Jordan (1930) and Stockwell (1940).
While after World War I the university accepted much responsibility for the housing of women, housing men was a more controversial subject. In 1920 a Housing Bureau for Men was established, and that office established as a goal the creation of sufficient dormitory space to house all incoming freshmen, both male and female. Debate over the topic continued, however, and in 1922 a group of alumni acted by opening Fletcher Hall as a residence for male students. In 1933 Fletcher Hall was acquired by the university, and in the late 1930s, with the construction of West and East Quads, the university accepted responsibility for providing housing for both male and female students.
The means to finance and administer an extensive housing plant have evolved over time. Originally dormitories were required to be financially self-supporting entities directly operated under the regents. The Depression made this arrangement untenable. The university pioneered a new financial and administrative structure in 1931 with the construction of Mosher-Jordan. The dormitory was paid for through a self-liquidating bond and control of the dormitory's finances and other matters was vested in a Board of Governors. This operational pattern was expanded in 1933, when all the women's residences except Martha Cook (the deed of gift for which guaranteed its independence) were consolidated into a single financial entity.
The post World War II expansion of the university put a tremendous strain on housing. The university responded with the construction of several new facilities. Alice Lloyd Hall (1949), South Quad (1951), Geddes House (1953), Oxford Housing (1963), and Bursley Hall (1968), helped cope with undergraduate students, Baits Housing (originally identified as Cedar Bend) (1966) was designed for upper classmen and graduate students.
At this time, there was a large number of married armed forces veterans enrolling at the university, creating a need for married housing. Being fully committed to meeting the educational needs of the veterans, the university initiated married student housing through the building of University Terrace in 1947 and the Northwood units in 1955, 1957, and 1958. Due to continued enrollment of the older, married student and the continuation of the GI bill, additional Northwood units were built in 1968 and 1972.
In 1962, the Reed committee, a committee to study student affairs at the university, called for continued commitment to quality housing but urged a phasing out of the "in loco parentis" role of the university. It was at this time, with the restructuring of the Office of Student Affairs, that housing became the responsibility of a single director in the Housing Division under the Vice President for Student Services, rather than the responsibility of the Dean of Men and the Dean of Women. The business, housekeeping, maintenance, and food service operations remained the responsibility of Financial Operations. In 1965, family housing was integrated into the Housing Division.
On July 1, 1966, the Office of University Housing was created, with John Feldkamp as director. The new office combined the responsibilities of Housing Division with those of Financial Operations. The Office of University Housing was then responsible for all aspects of university owned and affiliated housing. Relationships with the private market (off-campus housing) were maintained by the Office of Student Community relations.
In 1972, the Off-Campus Housing Office of the Housing Division was created as a result of the report of the Commission on Off-Campus Housing, created under President Harlan Hatcher in 1965. The commission's report urged the university to concern itself with the housing needs of all students, not just those in university owned and operated housing. The Off-Campus Housing Office acted as an informational agency: informing students on the availability of off-campus housing, advising on landlord-tenant concerns, and assuming responsibility for providing input to the university community regarding the off campus-student housing situation.
The 1937 Michigan House Plan was the ultimate factor in determining the objectives of housing at the university. The plan suggested that Housing should in some way contribute to student education, in addition to providing rooms. This was first implemented by naming residence units in honor of past faculty and by the opening of residence hall libraries. The goals of housing have continued to focus on education, student services, administrative and staff development. In the 1970s, educational needs continued to be addressed through residence education programs, residential academic programs, and residence hall libraries.
The Residence Hall Academic Peer Advisor Program was developed as a cooperative effort between Housing Division and the Academic Advising Office of the undergraduate College of Literature, Science and the Arts. The intent of the program was to meet criteria set by University Housing policy: academic interests of the residents must be served by programs and services offered in each residence hall. The first program was established at Markley Hall for the 1990/91 academic year. By 1996/97 the program expanded to a total of nine residence units.
Residence Halls Computing Program (ResComp) is a joint venture of the Information Technology Division and University Housing that started as a pilot project in the Mosher Jordan dormitories during the 1986/87 academic year. By May of 1986 approximately 150 Macintosh computers had been installed in eleven residence hall sites. ResComp student staff (trainers) lived in nine of the residence halls and taught classes on word processing and Michigan Terminal System (MTS) for approximately 10 hours per week. In 1991, ResComp sites were changed to 24 hour card access. Currently residence halls have in-room ethernet connectivity in addition to the computer centers.
Other areas implemented by Housing Division include Housing Food Service, Conference Management Services and the Entree and Entree Plus programs.
University Housing information is available on the World Wide Web at the URL http://www.housing.umich.edu/
Summary Contents List
Central Topical Files
1923-1978 (boxes 1-8)
1940-1989 (boxes 9-10)
1930-1994 (boxes 12-17)
1942-1992 (boxes 23-24)
1958-1995 (boxes 41-45)
Program Director Files (topical listing)
Topical Files
1925-1994 (boxes 38-39)
Reports
1965, 1980 (box 9)
1940-1979 (box 15)
1981-1982 (box 24)
1925-1990 (box 38)
Residence Halls (individual residence files)
1929-1971 (boxes 3-5)
1940-1987 (boxes 17-21)
Family Housing
1968-1989 (boxes 21-22)
Greek Housing (individual house files)
1971-1989 (boxes 10-11)
1950-1980 (boxes 22-23)
Financial Records
1930-1969 (boxes 25-31)
Bound Minutes
1939-1977 (boxes 32-35)
Visual Materials
Photographs (box 36, 45)
Videos (box 37)
Newspaper Clippings
Microfilm - reel 1 (1979-1990) [Bimu/B5 micro]
Scrapbook (1939-1949) [Bimu/B6]
Microfilm - reel 2 [BImu/B6 micro]
Reports -
The records of the Housing Division provide documentation on development and administration of the university's dormitory system, off-campus housing and student life. The records include correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, and other materials relating to administration of the office; include files relating to operation and naming of University dormitories, especially detailing the establishment of housing policy and the resolution of housing controversies; information on small group housing and off-campus housing with individual files on fraternities and sororities; also files concerning the occupational status and treatment of Japanese-Americans working for the University during World War II, and concerning the housing and training of military personnel on campus during the war.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Inter-Cooperative Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Japanese Americans--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Housing Division.; University of Michigan. Interfraternity Council.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; North Campus (University of Michigan); World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Residential College.; Adelia Cheever House (University of Michigan); Vera Baits Houses (University of Michigan); Betsey Barbour House (University of Michigan); Bursley Hall (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Martha Cook building.; Couzens Hall (University of Michigan); East Quadrangle (University of Michigan); Fletcher Hall (University of Michigan); Henderson House (University of Michigan); Lawyers' Club (University of Michigan); Alice Lloyd Hall (University of Michigan); Mary Markley Hall (University of Michigan); Helen Handy Newberry Residence (University of Michigan); Oxford Housing (University of Michigan); Stockwell Hall (University of Michigan); West Quadrangle (University of Michigan); Mosher-Jordan Halls (University of Michigan); South Quadrangle (University of Michigan)
Genre Terms:
College publications.
- Central Topical Files 1920-1978
  - 1920-1978
    The initial accessions of material from the Housing Office covered the years 1920-1978. They were received in many discreet accessions. In a major reprocessing of the records in 1986, the numerous accessions were arbitrarily arranged into a single alphabetical Central Topical Files series. Not surprisingly the topic most thoroughly documented in the Central Topical Files is student life within the university dormitory system. There is also much information about dormitory construction and governance. The latter topic covers a wide variety of social customs, but is particularly complete regarding the gradual lifting of special regulations affecting women and the gradual disappearance of gender specified dormitories. Four other topics are covered at some depth. Scattered throughout the records is information regarding race relations within the dormitories and the community. Second, there is a quantity of information regarding fraternities and sororities. Information includes consideration of the organizations' decline in the 1960s (and the subsequent impact on student housing that a loss of fraternity and sorority rooms would entail) and the proposed construction of fraternity and sorority houses on North Campus. Third, there is a large amount of information regarding the construction of Inter-Cooperative Council Sponsored housing on North Campus. Fourth, and more surprisingly, is a large body of personnel records relating to Japanese-Americans employed by the University during World War II. Many came to the university from Relocation Centers, and there is a small body of correspondence with individuals at these Centers.
    - Absent Percentages 1961-1962 (dormitory cafeteria) (Box 1)
    - Academic Opportunities 1966 (minorities) (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor
      - School Taxes 1969-1971 (Box 1)
      - Transportation Survey 1973 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development Housing Market Survey 1967 (Box 1)
    - Apartments 1963-1968 (Box 1)
    - Athletic Program 1966-1968 (training table expenses) (Box 1)
    - Bias Clause 1954-1958 (Box 1)
    - Board of Admissions 1966-1971 (Box 1)
    - Building Directors 1966-1971 (Box 1)
    - Building Histories 1967 (Box 1)
    - Building Program-Postwar Residence Halls circa 1944 (Box 1)
    - Building Services 1966-1971 (Box 1)
    - Capacities and Occupancies 1968 (Box 1)
    - Cinema Guild, "Flaming Creatures" 1967 (Box 1)
    - Coeducational Housing Proposal 1963-1970, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Committee on Underclass Experience, Final Report 1972 (Box 1)
    - Consultants 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Credit Union Housing Committee 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Day Care Centers 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - Dean of Women (Deborah Bacon) 1956-1961 (Box 1)
    - Discrimination Issue 1958 (Box 1)
    - Dormitory Financing 1928-1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Drinking Regulations 1920-1948, 1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Drugs 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Environmental Health and Safety Committee 1966-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Expansion of Affiliated Facilities 1968 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Housing 1947 (Box 2)
    - Fair Housing 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Fiscal Policy, UM-Ann Arbor 1974 (Box 2)
    - Fiscal Program re Housing 1967 (Box 2)
    - Food Riot 1956-1957, 1967, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Food Services
      - General 1968-1970 (Box 2)
      - Study 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Food Stores 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Fox Report 1968 (Box 2)
    - Fraternities and Sororities 1942-1973, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Freshman Program Committee 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - General Housing Services Questionnaire 1970 (Box 2)
    - Goals 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Health Service 1968-1971, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Housing
      - Data 1944-1959 (Box 2)
      - Survey among Graduate Students 1955 (Box 2)
      - Survey, Central Campus Area 1964 (Box 2)
      - Survey 1965 (Box 2)
      - Survey 1970 (Box 2)
    - Housing Facilities
      - Alumnae House 1946-1950 (Mary Markley house) (Box 3)
      - Sarah Caswell Angell House 1948-1955 (Box 3)
      - Baits Housing 1964-1970 (Cedar Bend Project), 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Betsey Barbour House 1923-1954, 2 folders (Box 3)
        (See Also Helen Newberry)
      - Bursley Hall 1957-1972, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Cambridge Hall 1960-1962 (Box 3)
      - Adelia Cheever House 1939-1958 (Box 3)
      - Martha Cook Building 1930-1956 (Box 3)
      - Couzens Hall 1955-1960, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - East Quad 1960 (Box 3)
      - Fletcher Hall 1921-1924, 1955, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Floor Plans, Miscellaneous Residences (Box 3)
      - Geddes House 1960-1964, 2 folders (Box 3)
        (See Also Oxford Housing)
      - Henderson House 1950-1961 (Box 3)
      - International Center, 1948-1969, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Jordan Hall 1948-1955 (Box 4)
      - Carol Hubbard Kleinstueck House 1949-1954 (Box 4)
      - Alice Lloyd 1947-1961 (Box 4)
      - Alfred Henry Lloyd House (Box 4)
      - Mary Markley Hall 1956-1964, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Medical Dormitory 1938 (Box 4)
      - Mosher Hall 1943-1955 (Box 4)
      - Helen Newberry, 1933-1969 (Box 4)
        (includes Betsey Barbour materials)
      - Oxford Housing 1961-1967, 4 folders (Box 4)
        (See Also Geddes House)
      - Northwood I-IV 1953-1970, 13 folders (Box 4)
      - Northwood IV 1966-1967, 1 folders (Box 5)
      - Alice Freeman Palmer House 1950 (Box 5)
      - Pilot Project 1963 (Box 5)
      - Residential College 1966 (Box 5)
      - Stockwell Hall 1938-1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - South Quad 1951-1952 (Box 5)
      - University House 1943-1949 (Box 5)
      - Victor Vaughan 1962 (Box 5)
      - Veteran's Housing Project 1950 (Box 5)
    - Human Relations (Negro Recruiting) 1966-1969 (Box 5)
    - Income Restrictions 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - Inter-Cooperative Council, North Campus Project, 1966-1969, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Inventory of Space 1967 (Box 5)
    - Joint University-City Conference 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - Lease Booklets 1951-1966 (Box 5)
    - Mailings to Students Helpful Hints for the Hitched, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Plan Re-evaluation 1957 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1926-1971 (Box 5)
    - Northwood Terrace Residents Association 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Occupancy Procedures 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - Off-Campus Housing Program 1957-1962 (Box 5)
    - Office of the Business Manager of Residence Halls
      - Annual Report 1939-1951, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Personal, F.C. Shiel 1968 (Box 5)
    - Office of Religious Affairs 1968-1973 (Box 5)
    - Office of Student Services
      - General 1970-1978 (Box 5)
    - Office of Student Services, cont. (Box 6)
      - Directors Meetings 1973-1976, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Policy Board 1970-1974, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Orientation 1966-1971 (Box 6)
    - Parent's Orientation 1966-1971 (Box 6)
    - Personnel
      - General 1967-1973 (Box 6)
      - Draft 1967 (Selective Service) (Box 6)
      - Japanese Americans
        - List of Employees 1943-1944, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Occupational Deferment 1943-1944, 4 folders (Box 6)
        - Personal Security Questionnaires 1943-1944, 3 folders (Box 6)
        - Provost Marshall 1944 (Box 6)
        - Relocation Center Correspondence 1943-1944, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Japanese Faculty Housing 1942-1945 (Box 6)
      - Staff Selection Procedures 1969-1972 (Box 6)
    - Pilot Program 1967-1970 (Box 6)
    - Planning for Adequate Housing Supply 1967-1970 (Box 6)
    - Police 1966-1970 (Box 6)
    - President's Commission
      - 1965 (Box 6)
      - 1967 (Box 6)
    - Race Relations 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Rates
      - General 1960-1966 (Box 7)
      - Rate Study Committee 1956-1958 (Box 7)
    - Reapplication Procedure 1967 (Box 7)
    - Recreation 1964-1974, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Rent Strike 1969-1970 (Box 7)
    - Rental Property Association of Ann Arbor 1966-1968 (Box 7)
    - Residence Halls
      - Assemblies 1955-1970, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Board of Governors 1955-1970, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - General Policies 1958-1963 (Box 7)
      - Reports 1939-1942 (Box 7)
      - Subcommittee to Evaluate Men's Residence Halls 1957-1959 (folder 1) (Box 7)
    - Residence Halls, cont. (Box 8)
      - Subcommittee to Evaluate Men's Residence Halls 1957-1959 (folders 2-3) (Box 8)
      - Libraries 1962-1970, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - Hall Floor Plans 1940 (Box 8)
    - Room Change Policy 1966-1968 (Box 8)
    - Room Search Policies 1970-1972 (Box 8)
    - Safety 1968-1971 (Box 8)
    - Security 1968-1973, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Sex Education 1968 (Box 8)
    - Staff Policies 1955-1965 (Box 8)
    - Staff Responsibilities 1962 (Box 8)
    - State Auditor General 1969 (Box 8)
    - Summer School 1970 (Box 8)
    - Student Government Council 1967-1969 (Box 8)
    - Student Judiciary 1969 (Box 8)
    - Student Records 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Union Activity 1967-1970 (Box 8)
    - University Housing Committee 1966-1967 (Box 8)
    - University Housing Procedures 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Vice-President of Student Affairs
      - Cutler, Richard 1967-1968 (Box 8)
      - Newell, Barbara 1968-1970 (Box 8)
    - Women 1961 (class booklet, THE 59ERS) (Box 8)
    - Women's Conference Committee 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - Women's Hours and Rules 1944-1946, 1966-1971, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Work Progress Administration (WPA) Progress Reports 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - World War II
      - Blackout Instructions 1943 (Box 8)
      - Emergency Training 1942-1946, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1940-1993
    The Central Topical Files, 1940-1993 subseries (1.25 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically. The records appear to be from the Off-Campus Housing Office of the Housing Division. Off-Campus housing refers to housing in the university community that is not owned and operated by the University of Michigan. Included in this category are apartments, rental houses, and small group housing. Small group housing refers to fraternities, sororities, and student owned and operated cooperatives, of which the university has more interaction. The researcher interested individual small group housing units should look at the Small Group Housing series, immediately following.
    The bulk of the files deal with off-campus housing, however, there are some files relating to residence halls. Within the "Off-Campus Housing" files, the researcher will find information on the Off-Campus Housing Registration Program, inspection reports of off-campus rental units, leases for fraternities and sororities and Inter-Cooperative materials. The Off-Campus Housing Registration program was designed by the Housing Information Office to identify those rental property owners or managers who wished to rent to students in a program of cooperation with the university. To become registered, rental units had to be certified by the city, agree to use the rental lease agreement or an approved private lease, comply with non-discriminating standards and agree to use the University of Michigan Mediation Service to resolve tenant-landlord disputes. The "Registered Buildings" folder contains a list from 1989 of registered landlords and the number of units they rented.
    The "Inter-Cooperative Council" files contain historical materials, housing inspection reports, and membership contracts. Of particular interest in the "Residence Hall-Rates" file is a list of residence hall rates spanning the years 1940/41 through 1992/93.
    - Ann Arbor Apartment Association 1983-1989 (Box 9)
    - Community/Fraternity Relations 1980-1986 (Box 9)
    - Discrimination 1951-1965 (re: fraternities) (Box 9)
    - Educational Programming 1974-1976 (Box 9)
    - Family Housing Rates 1992 (Box 9)
    - Fraternity Census
      - 1987 (Box 9)
      - 1988 (Box 9)
      - 1989 (Box 9)
    - Fraternities 1963-1985 (Box 9)
    - Goals and Objectives 1980-1988 (Box 9)
    - Henderson House Board of Governor's Minutes (1980-1984) (Box 9)
    - Housing Services Questionnaire 1971-1974 (Box 9)
    - Housing Statistics 1992-1993 (Box 9)
    - Inter-Cooperative Council (ICC)
      - General 1968-1979 (Box 9)